Living in Africa is to be on the edge,
إن العيش في افريقيا هو بمثابة العيش على الحافة
metaphorically, and quite literally
مجازا، وحرفيا إلى حد بعيد
when you think about connectivity before 2008.
عندما نتذكر وسائل الاتصال قبل 2008.
Though many human intellectual and technological leaps
على الرغم من القفزات الفكرية والتكنولوجية للإنسان
had happened in Europe and the rest of the world,
التي حدثت في أوروبا وبقية دول العالم.
but Africa was sort of cut off.
فأفريقيا كانت نوعا ما منفصلة عن ذلك.
And that changed, first with ships
و لقد تغير ذلك بداية من السفن
when we had the Renaissance, the Scientific Revolution
بعد عصر النهضة والثورة العلمية
and also the Industrial Revolution.
وأيضا الثورة الصناعية.
And now we've got the digital revolution.
والآن لدينا الثورة الرقمية
These revolutions have not been evenly distributed
هذه الثورات لم تحدث بشكل متساو
across continents and nations.
عبر القارات والدول.
Never have been.
مُطلقا.
Now, this is a map of the undersea fiber optic cables
الآن هذه خريطة كابلات الألياف البصرية تحت البحر
that connect Africa to the rest of the world.
والتي توصل أفريقيا ببقية دول العالم.
What I find amazing is that Africa
والأمر الذي أدهشني أن أفريقيا
is transcending its geography problem.
تحاول أن تتجاوز مشكلتها الجغرافية.
Africa is connecting to the rest of the world
إن أفريقيا على اتصال ببقية العالم
and within itself.
وداخلها أيضا.
The connectivity situation has improved greatly,
لقد تحسن وضع الاتصال إلى حد كبير،
but some barriers remain.
ولكن لا تزال هناك بعض الحواجز.
It is with this context that Ushahidi came to be.
وانطلاقا من هذا السياق بدأ برنامج أوشاهيدي.
In 2008, one of the problems that we faced
في عام 2008، كانت إحدى المشاكل التي واجهتنا
was lack of information flow.
هي قلة تدفق المعلومات.
There was a media blackout in 2008,
كان هناك تعتيم اعلامي سنة 2008
when there was post-election violence in Kenya.
بعد أحداث العنف عقب الانتخابات في كينيا
It was a very tragic time. It was a very difficult time.
لقد كان وقتا مأساويا جدا. و صعبا للغاية.
So we came together and we created software
لذا اجتمعنا معا وأنشأنا برنامجا
called Ushahidi.
أسميناه أوشاهيدي.
And Ushahidi means "testimony" or "witness" in Swahili.
ومعنى أوشاهيدي هو " الشاهد" باللغة السواحيلية.
I'm very lucky to work with two amazing collaborators.
وكنت محظوظة للغاية لعملي مع اثنين من شركائي المذهلين.
This is David and Erik.
هما "ديفيد" و "اريك".
I call them brothers from another mother.
أنا أعتبرهم أشقاء من أم أخرى.
Clearly I have a German mother somewhere.
من الواضح أن لدي أما ألمانية في مكان ما.
And we worked together first with building
وعملنا مع بعضنا في البداية لإنشاء
and growing Ushahidi.
وتنمية أوشاهيدي.
And the idea of the software was to gather information
وقامت فكرة البرنامج على تجميع المعلومات
from SMS, email and web, and put a map
من الرسائل النصية والبريد الإلكتروني و شبكة الأنترنيت، ووضع خريطة
so that you could see what was happening where,
تمكنك من معرفة ومشاهدة ما الذي يحدث وأين يحدث،
and you could visualize that data.
وبإمكانكم رؤية تلك البيانات.
And after that initial prototype,
وبعد هذا النموذج الأولي،
we set out to make free and open-source software
قررنا جعل البرنامج مجاني ومفتوح المصدر
so that others do not have to start from scratch like we did.
حتى لا يضطر الآخرون للبدء من الصفر كما فعلنا.
All the while, we also wanted to give back
وفي نفس الوقت، أردنا أيضا رد الجميل
to the local tech community that helped us
لمجتمع التكنولوجيا المحلية الذي ساعدنا
grow Ushahidi and supported us in those early days.
على تنمية "أوشاهيدي" ودعمنا في الأيام الأولى للبرنامج.
And that's why we set up the iHub in Nairobi,
ولهذا السبب أنشأنا مجمّعا رقميا (آي هاب) في نيروبي
an actual physical space
في مكان على أرض الواقع
where we could collaborate,
حيث يمكننا التعاون سوية،
and it is now part of an integral tech ecosystem in Kenya.
وهو الآن جزء لا يتجزأ من نظام التكنولوجيا البيئية في كينيا.
We did that with the support of different organizations
وقد فعلنا ذلك بدعم من مختلف المنظمات
like the MacArthur Foundation and Omidyar Network.
مثل مؤسسة ماك آرثر وشبكة أوميديار.
And we were able to grow this software footprint,
واستطعنا أن نضع البصمة الأولى لهذا البرنامج،
and a few years later it became
وبعد عدة سنوات أصبح
very useful software,
برنامجا مفيدا جدا،
and we were quite humbled when it was used in Haiti
و شعرنا بالتواضع عندما استُخدم البرنامج في هايتي
where citizens could indicate where they are
عندما تمكن المواطنون معرفة أماكنهم
and what their needs were,
واحتياجاتهم،
and also to deal with the fallout from the nuclear crisis
وتمكنوا أيضا من التعامل مع تداعيات الكارثة النووية
and the tsunami in Japan.
والمد البحري في اليابان.
Now, this year the Internet turns 20,
وهذه السنة بلغ عمر الأنترنيت 20 عاما،
It is the team, and it's also the community
وبلغ عمر فريق أوشاهيدي الخمس سنوات. إنه فريق ومجتمع كذلك
that uses this technology in ways that we could not foresee.
يستخدم هذه التقنية بطرق لا يمكننا التنبؤ بها.
We did not imagine that there would be this many maps
لم نتخيل وجود هذا العدد الكبير من الخرائط
around the world.
في العالم أجمع.
There are crisis maps, election maps, corruption maps,
فهناك خرائط توضيحية للأزمات وللإنتخابات وللفساد
and even environmental monitoring crowd maps.
وأيضا للرصد البيئي للسكان والتجمعات.
We are humbled that this has roots in Kenya
ونشعر بالتواضع لتواجد جذور هذا العمل في كينيا
and that it has some use to people around the world
ولاستخدام الناس له في جميع أنحاء العالم
trying to figure out the different issues that they're dealing with.
لاكتشاف ومعرفة القضايا المختلفة التي يواجهونها.
There is more that we're doing to explore this idea
ونحن نبذل الكثير من الجهد لنكتشف أكثر عن فكرة
of collective intelligence, that I, as a citizen,
الإستخبارات الجماعية، والتي تعني أني- كمواطنة -
if I share the information with whatever device that I have,
إذا قمت بمشاركة المعلومات باستخدام أي جهاز
could inform you about what is going on,
فهذا سيُمكّنك من معرفة الذي يحدث،
and that if you do the same, we can have a bigger picture
وأنك إذا فعلت ذلك بالمثل فإن الصورة ستصبح أكثر وضوحا
of what's going on.
عما نريد معرفته.
I moved back to Kenya in 2011.
لقد عدت إلى كينيا عام 2011.
Erik moved in 2010.
وعاد "إريك" عام 2010.
Very different reality. I used to live in Chicago
وكان الواقع مختلفا كثيرا. فقد كنت أعيش في "شيكاغو"
where there was abundant Internet access.
حيث كان الإتصال بالأنترنيت أمرا متوفرا.
I had never had to deal with a blackout.
ولم يحدث لي أن واجهت أي انقطاع للتيار الكهربائي.
And in Kenya, it's a very different reality,
ولكن في كينيا كان الأمر يجري على نحو مختلف،
and one thing that remains despite the leaps in progress
والشيء الوحيد الذي لم يتغير برغم قفزات التطور السريعة
and the digital revolution is the electricity problem.
والثورة الرقمية التي حدثت هو مشكلة الكهرباء.
The day-to-day frustrations of dealing with this
إن الاحباط المتكرر يوما بعد يوم من التعامل مع هذا الأمر
can be, let's just say very annoying.
يمكن أن نقول عنه أنه شيء مزعج للغاية.
Blackouts are not fun.
فانقطاع التيار الكهربائي ليس بالشيء الممتع.
Imagine sitting down to start working, and all of a sudden
تخيل أنك جالس لتبدأ العمل، وفجأة ودون إنذار
the power goes out,
ينقطع التيار الكهربائي,
your Internet connection goes down with it,
وينقطع معه اتصالك بالإنترنت،
so you have to figure out, okay, now, where's the modem,
لذا تبدأ في السؤال، حسنا، والآن أين المودم،
how do I switch back?
وكيف يمكنني أن أعاود اتصالي بالأنترنيت؟
And then, guess what? You have to deal with it again.
و هل تعرف أيضا؟ ستواجه هذه المشكلة مرات أخرى أيضا.
Now, this is the reality of Kenya, where we live now,
هذا هو الواقع في كينيا، حيث نعيش الآن،
and other parts of Africa.
وكذلك الحال بالنسبة لأجزاء من أفريقيا.
The other problem that we're facing
والمشكلة الأخرى التي نواجهها
is that communication costs are also still a challenge.
هي تكاليف الإتصال التي تعتبر بمثابة تحدي.
It costs me five Kenyan shillings,
إنها تكلفني بالعملة الكندية 5 شلنات،
or .06 USD to call the U.S., Canada or China.
أو 0.6 دولار أمريكي ثمن الإتصال بأمريكا أو كندا أو الصين.
Guess how much it costs to call Rwanda, Ghana, Nigeria?
خمن الثمن إذا للاتصال برواندا أو غانا أو نيجيريا؟
Thirty Kenyan shillings. That's six times the cost
إنها تكلف 30 شلن بالعملة الكينية، وهذا يمثل ستة أضعاف
to connect within Africa.
تكلفة الإتصال بأفريقيا.
And also, when traveling within Africa,
وأيضا، عندما تسافر عبر أفريقيا،
you've got different settings for different mobile providers.
يجب عليك أن تغير الإعدادات المختلفة لكل خدمات التنقل
This is the reality that we deal with.
هذا هو الواقع الذي نتعامل معه.
So we've got a joke in Ushahidi
لذلك ابتكرنا مزحة في مشروع "أوشاهيدي"
where we say, "If it works in Africa, it'll work anywhere."
عندما قلنا: "إذا اشتغل في أفريقيا فسيعمل في أي مكان."
[Most use technology to define the function. We use function to drive the technology.]
[الكثير يستخدمون التكنولوجيا لتحديد الوظيفة. نحن نستخدم الوظيفة لنحرك التكنولوجيا.]
What if we could overcome the problem
ماذا إذا تخطينا مشكلة
of unreliable Internet and electricity
الكهرباء والأنترنيت الغير موثوق بهما
and reduce the cost of connection?
وقللنا تكاليف الاتصال؟
Could we leverage the cloud?
هل يمكننا الاستفادة من السحاب؟
We've built a crowd map, we've built Ushahidi.
لقد أنشأنا خريطة للتجمعات, لقد أنشأنا أوشاهيدي.
Could we leverage these technologies
هل يمكننا الإستفادة من هذه التكنولوجيا
to switch smartly whenever you travel from country to country?
للتبديل بذكاء في أي وقت تسافر فيه من بلد إلى أخرى؟
So we looked at the modem,
لذا نظرنا الى المودم،
an important part of the infrastructure of the Internet,
وهو الشيء الأساسي للإتصال بالأنترنيت،
and asked ourselves why
وسألنا أنفسنا
the modems that we are using right now
لماذا يُستخدم هذا المودم الذي نستعمله
are built for a different context, where you've got
في محيط مختلف، وفي أماكن حيث تتواجد
ubiquitous internet, you've got ubiquitous electricity,
فيها الكهرباء والإنترنت في كل مكان،
yet we sit here in Nairobi and we do not have that luxury.
بينما نحن هنا في نيروبي لا نحظى بهذه الرفاهية.
We wanted to redesign the modem
لقد أردنا أن نعيد تصميم المودم
for the developing world, for our context,
لتناسب العالم النامي، وتناسب محيطنا،
and for our reality.
وواقعنا.
What if we could have connectivity with less friction?
ماذا إذا أمكننا التواصل مع مقدار أقل من الإحتكاك؟
This is the BRCK.
هذا هو الـ BRCK
It acts as a backup to the Internet
وهو يعمل كنسخة احتياطية للأنترنيت
so that, when the power goes out,
فعندما ينقطع التيار الكهربائي،
it fails over and connects to the nearest GSM network.
تنفصل تلقائيا لتتصل بأقرب شبكة جي إس إم.
Mobile connectivity in Africa is pervasive.
إن الاتصالات المتنقلة في أفريقيا واسعة الإنتشار.
It's actually everywhere.
وهي كذلك في كل مكان.
Most towns at least have a 3G connection.
ومعظم المدن لديها على الأقل شبكة اتصال الجيل الثالث 3G
So why don't we leverage that? And that's why we built this.
فلماذا لا نستفيد من ذلك؟ ولذلك قررنا إنشاء هذا
The other reason that we built this
والسبب الآخر الذي جعلنا ننشئ هذا
is when electricity goes down, this has eight hours
أنه عندما يُفصل التيار الكهربائي، فإنه يظل في البطارية
of battery left, so you can continue working,
شحن لمدة 8 ساعات، فيمكنك الاستمرار بالعمل،
you can continue being productive,
والاستمرار بإنتاجك وعملك،
and let's just say you are less stressed.
دعنا نقل أنك الآن أقل توترا.
And for rural areas, it can be
وبالنسبة للمناطق الريفية، فإن ذلك سيكون
the primary means of connection.
الوسيلة الأساسية للاتصال.
The software sensibility at Ushahidi is still at play
لايزال برنامج استشعار أوشاهيدي يعمل
when we wondered how can we use the cloud
عندما تساءلنا كيف يمكننا أن نستفيد من المشكلات
to be more intelligent so that
لنكون أكثر ذكاء.
you can analyze the different networks,
لذلك، بإمكانك أن تحلل الشبكات المختلفة،
and whenever you switch on the backup,
وحينما تبدأ بالعمل على النسخة الإحتياطية،
you pick on the fastest network,
تقوم باختيار الشبكة الأسرع،
so we'll have multi-SIM capability
لذا سيكون لدينا بطاقة متعددة القدرات
so that you can put multiple SIMs,
بحيث يمكنك وضع بطاقات عديدة،
and if one network is faster, that's the one you hop on,
وإذا وجدت الشبكة الأسرع، فإنك ستتصل بها تلقائيا،
and if the up time on that is not very good,
وإذا كانت ليست جيدة في ذاك الوقت،
then you hop onto the next one.
فإنك تنتقل تلقائيا للأخرى.
The idea here is for you to be able to connect anywhere.
تتمثل الفكرة هنا في إتاحة اتصالك بالأنترنيت في أي وقت.
With load balancing, this can be possible.
ومع موازنة التحميل، يكون هذا ممكنا.
The other interesting thing for us -- we like sensors --
والأمر الآخر المثير للإهتمام - نحن نحب أجهزة الإستشعار -
is this idea that you could have an on-ramp
هو فكرة امتلاك تشويش هوائي
for the Internet of things.
لأنترنيت الأشياء.
Imagine a weather station that can be attached to this.
تخيل إذا اتصلت محطة طقس بهذا.
It's built in a modular way so that you can also attach
إنها مبنية على طريقة وحدات نمطية تمكنك من ربط
a satellite module so that you could have
قمر صناعي نمطي بها لتبقى
Internet connectivity even in very remote areas.
على اتصال بالإنترنت حتى اثناء وجودك في مناطق بعيدة
Out of adversity can come innovation,
إن الحاجة هي أم الإختراع،
and how can we help the ambitious coders and makers
وكيف يمكننا مساعدة المبرمجين والعاملين المحترفين
in Kenya to be resilient in the face of problematic infrastructure?
في كينيا ليكونوا قادرين على الصمود في وجه مشاكل البنية التحتية؟
And for us, we begin with solving the problem
بالنسبة لنا، لقد بدأنا في حل هذه المشكلة
in our own backyard in Kenya.
في باحتنا الخلفية في كينيا.
It is not without challenge.
ولم تكن بالأمر اليسير.
Our team has basically been mules carrying components
لقد كان فريقنا بشكل أساسي ينقل معدات
from the U.S. to Kenya. We've had very interesting conversations
من أمريكا إلى كينيا. ولقد أثرنا محادثة مشوقة
with customs border agents.
مع وكلاء حدود الجمارك.
"What are you carrying?"
"ما الذي تحملونه؟"
And the local financing is not
والتمويل المحلي ليس جزء
part of the ecosystem for supporting hardware projects.
من التنظيم البيئي الذي يدعم منتجات الأجهزة.
So we put it on Kickstarter, and I'm happy to say that,
لذلك وضعناها في كيكستارتر، وأنا سعيدة لأقول أنه
through the support of many people,
بمساعدة الكثير من الناس،
not only here but online,
ممن ليسوا من هنا ولكن على الأنترنيت أيضا،
the BRCK has been Kickstarted,
تم وضع BRCK على كيكستارتر،
and now the interesting part of bringing this to market begins.
وقد بدأ الآن الجزء المشوق لإحضار هذا إلى الأسواق.
I will close by saying that, if we solve this
وسأختم قائلة، أننا إذا جلبنا هذا
for the local market, it could be impactful
للسوق المحلي، سيكون هذا مؤثرا
not only for the coders in Nairobi
ليس فقط للمبرمجين في نايروبي
but also for small business owners
ولكن لأصحاب المشاريع الصغيرة أيضا
who need reliable connectivity,
ممن يحتاجون لمصدر آمن للاتصال،
and it can reduce the cost of connecting,
وبإمكانه تقليل تكلفة الاتصال،
and hopefully collaboration within African countries.
آملين التعاون مع الدول الأفريقية.
The idea is that the building blocks of the digital economy
والفكرة هنا هو أن لبنات بناء الاقتصاد القومي
are connectivity and entrepreneurship.
هما الاتصال وريادة الأعمال.
The BRCK is our part
ومشروع BRCK هو الجزء المخصص لنا
to keep Africans connected,
لنبقي أفريقيا متصلة بالعالم،
and to help them drive the global digital revolution.
ونساعدهم على قيادة الثورة الرقمية العالمية.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)